Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Writings and Notes, circa 1895-1964, Series 3:; (Box 6-9; 3.3 linear feet)
  - Writings and Notes by Kathrine Sanger Brinley, circa 1895-1964, Subseries 3.2:
    Writings by Kathrine Sanger Brinley primarily document her daily life, travels, and thoughts on religion. Included are 15 diaries, some very small pocket-sized books, in which she recorded daily events and thoughts. Several of the diaries describe the period she and Daniel Putnam Brinley were living in Paris and Florence. The diary from 1908 also includes color illustrations by Daniel Putnam Brinley. Many of the later diaries contain loose items within the pages, such as postcards and news clippings. Within "A Diary of Private Prayer" Kathrine wrote her daily thoughts on her religious practice. Writings by Kathrine also include several notebooks, primarily from the period the Brinley's were living in Europe; travel notes from Europe written on the back of numerous postcards; travel essays about her travels in Bermuda in 1921; poetry; autobiographical essays; notes on religion; engagement calendars; and miscellanous writings and fragments.
    - Diaries, 1901-1906, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 36-39)
    - Diaries, 1907-1929, (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
    - Diaries, 1940-1964, (7 folders) (Box 7, Folder 5-11)
    - Diary, "A Diary of Private Prayer", 1960 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Notebooks, circa 1903-1908, 1960-1963, (7 folders) (Box 7, Folder 13-19)
    - Notebook, (Includes sketches by Daniel Putnam Brinley), circa 1907-1908 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - School Notebook, "Junior A. Literature", circa 1895 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Notes about Religion, 1918-1958 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Notes, 1901-1960s, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
    - Travel Notes from Europe, circa 1905-1908, (4 folders) (Box 8, Folder 4-7)
    - Writings about Bermuda, circa 1921 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Poetry, 1903-1937 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - "Items & Incidents in the Story of My Life", circa 1900 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - "A Literary Quartette", circa 1900 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - "Fairy Hunting in Normandy", circa early-1900s (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - "Datchet House", circa 1914 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - "The Spoken Word", circa 1930s (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - "Journal of Gordon Brinley: Summer, 1939", 1939 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - "Mrs. Patrick Campbell, Famous British Actress Dies at 75", 1940 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - "Publicity for New Canaan Library Exhibition", 1954 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1910-1930, (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 18-22)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1931-1945, (7 folders) (Box 8, Folder 23-29)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1946-1964, (12 folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-12)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, 1986-circa 1950s, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 13-14)
- Commission Files, 1920-1979, Series 4:; (Box 9-10; 0.8 linear feet)
  Commission files concern specific mural commissions of Daniel Putnam Brinley and may contain correspondence, specifications, lists, contracts, financial agreements and receipts, notes, publicity and clippings, plans, sketches, and photographs of the finished murals. Two commissions for which extensive documentation can be found are the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company murals in New York and the Liberty War Memorial in Kansas City Missouri. Detailed original mural studies for the Metropolitan Life Insurance commission is filed in Series 9: Artwork.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Hudson Motor Car Company of New York, Inc., 1920 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - St. Mark's Parish, New Canaan, Connecticut, 1922-1961 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Maillard's Restaurant, Chicago, Illinois, 1924 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Fordham Lutheran Church, New York, 1925-1928 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Liberty Memorial, Kansas City, Missouri, 1925-1977, (4 folders) (Box 9, Folder 19-22)
  - Bank of New York & Trust Co., 1928 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Brooklyn Savings Bank, New York, 1928-1939, 1975, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - News Building, New York, New York, 1929-1938 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 120 Wall Street, New York, 1930-1931 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Saint George's Episcopal Church, Bridgeport, Connecticut, 1931-1953, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - Post Office, Bridgeport, Connecticut, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, New York, 1932-1973, (6 folders) (Box 10, Folder 8-13)
  - Blakely, Georgia, Post Office, 1937-1939, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - St. Paul's Church, Norwalk, Connecticut, 1947-1959, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Wayside Cross, New Canaan, Connecticut, 1950-1957 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Community Baptist Church, New Canaan, Connecticut, 1954-1974 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Trinity Church, Swarthmore, Pennsylvania, 1955-1956 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Congregational Church, New Canaan, Connecticut, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Organization Files, 1909-1964, Series 5:; (Box 10-11; 0.9 linear feet)
  Organization files document the Brinleys' participation and membership in arts and social organizations, and Daniel Putnam Brinley's executive and administrative positions in many of these organizations. Files may include correspondence, reports, bulletins, newsletters, invitations, exhibition catalogs, constitutions and by-laws, and member lists. Files for the Beaux-Arts Institute of Design and the Silvermine Guild of Artists also contain group photographs which include the Brinleys.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety. For some published items, only the covers have been scanned.
  - Architectural League of New York, 1923-1963, (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 20-22)
  - Beaux-Arts Institute of Design, 1913-1945, (4 folders) (Box 10, Folder 23-26)
  - The Coffee House, 1921-1964, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 27-28)
  - Edward MacDowell Association (MacDowell Club), 1911-1963, (4 folders) (Box 10, Folder 29-32)
  - Grand Central Art Galleries (Painters and Sculptors Gallery Association), 1923-1954 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - National Academy of Design, 1940-1964, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - National Arts Club, 1910-1964, (3 folders) (Box 11, Folder 4-6)
  - National Soap Sculpture Committee, 1941-1958 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - National Society of Mural Painters, 1923-1964, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
  - New Canaan Garden Club, 1918-1962, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 10-11)
  - Silvermine Guild of Artists, 1909-1964, (3 folders) (Box 11, Folder 12-14)
- Financial and Legal Records, 1896-1965, Series 6:; (Box 11; 0.4 linear feet)
  Financial and legal records include account books, expenditure notebooks, bills and receipts, leases, power of attorney documents, and scattered social security, stock, banking, and tax records. There are legal and financial records regarding Datchet House, the Brinleys' home in New Canaan, Connecticut, including documents concerning construction and the eventual sale of the house. Also found are publication agreements and royalty statements for the four travel books written by Kathrine Sanger Brinley. Additionally, this series contains estate settlement records for two of Daniel Putnam Brinley's relatives.
  This series has been partially scanned. Items not scanned include bills and receipts, estate records, banking documents, earning statements, royalty reports, social security documents, tax records, and stock records.
  - Account Book, 1906-1907 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Bank Statements, 1934, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1896-1965, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 17-18)
  - Court Documents, 1942-1943 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Documents regarding Construction of Datchet House, 1913-1914, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 20-21)
  - Documents regarding Sale of Datchet House, 1944-1945 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Documents regarding Sale of Land, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Earning Statements, 1919, 1945, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Estate Records, Putnam Brinley (Uncle of Daniel Putnam Brinley), 1913-1914, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 25-26)
  - Estate Records, Samuel D. Bradford, 1912-1941, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 27-28)
  - Leases, 1909-1944, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 29-30)
  - Notebook of Expenditures, 1905 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Notes on Finances, circa 1910s-1940s (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Power of Attorney, 1917-1918 (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - Publication Agreements, 1934-1936 (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - Records of Checks Drawn, 1910-1949, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Royalty Reports, 1937-1946, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Social Security Documents, 1951, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Stock Records, 1917-1944, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Tax Documents, 1914-1957, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - Warehouse Lists, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous Legal Documents, 1896-1935 (Box 11, Folder 41)
- Printed Material, 1895-1979, Series 7:; (Box 11-13, OV 16-17; 1.8 linear feet)
  Printed Material consists of published books, including Ruines de Guerre containing illustrations by Brinley of war damages in France published by the Y.M.C.A., exhibition catalogs and announcements; printed materials related to travel; event brochures, programs, and invitations; news clippings; religious publications; newsletters and reports from organizations; and magazines. There is an issue of Alfred Stieglitz's magazine Camera Work with a handwritten inscription to Brinley from Stieglitz.
  Portions of this series have been scanned. Items not scanned include some books, travel publications, postcards, programs, religious publications, and reproductions of artwork. For some published items, only the covers have been scanned.
  - Book, About the Neighborhood and Other Things, circa 1919 (Box 11, Folder 42)
  - Book, Extracts from Papers of the Society of Painters in Tempera, 1927 (Box 11, Folder 43)
  - Book, Faith Through Love, 1896, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 44)
  - Book, Ruines de Guerre, 1919, (Oversized housed in OV 17) (Box 11, Folder 45)
  - Book, St. Mark's and Its Forebears The First 200 Years, 1964, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 46)
  - Book, The Story of the Armory Show, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Brochures and Maps from Travels, 1904-1975, (Not scanned) (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Brochures, Miscellaneous, 1910-circa 1960s (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin of the National Arts Club, 1921-1962, (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
  - Event Invitations & Announcements (Non-Art Related), 1892, circa 1932-1940s (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1905-1963, (7 folders) (Box 12, Folder 7-13)
  - Undated Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, circa 1900-1955 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Entry Forms & Guidelines, 1914-1964 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Magazine, "Camera Work", 1915 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Magazines, Miscellaneous, 1914-1919, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Map from John Erskine's Book, Penelope's Man, 1928, (Oversized housed in OV 16; not scanned) (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - News Clippings, 1897-1914, (6 folders) (Box 12, Folder 19-24)
  - News Clippings, 1915-1937, (7 folders) (Box 12, Folder 25-31)
  - News Clippings, 1938-1979, (2 folders) (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Undated News Clippings, circa 1897-1966 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters and Reports, 1914-1940 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Postcards, circa 1900-1960, (Not scanned) (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Printed Material about Judy Bell, circa 1963 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material about Mosaics, 1907, circa 1934 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material about New Canaan, Connecticut, 1934-1968 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Printed Material about Solon Borglum, circa 1923, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Printed Material from Trip to London, 1927, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 13, Folder 10-11)
  - Programs, 1895-1962, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
  - Religious Publications & Sermons, 1899-1974, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 13, Folder 14-15)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Daniel Putnam Brinley, circa 1930s, (Not scanned) (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1909-1968, (Oversized materials housed in OV 16; not scanned) (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Map from John Erskine's Book, Penelope's Man, 1928, (Oversized from Box 12, F18)) (Box OV 16)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1909-1968, (Oversized from Box 13, F17) (Box OV 16)
  - Book, Ruines de Guerre, 1919, (Oversized removed from Box 11, F45) (Box OV 17)
- Photographs, 1881-1971, Series 8:; (Box 13-14, OV 22; 0.8 linear feet)
  This series contains photographs of Daniel Putnam Brinley, Kathrine Sanger Brinley, their travels, residences, and artwork. Portraits of Daniel Putnam Brinley depict him as a child and young man, and working on mural projects. Several portraits of Kathrine Sanger Brinley depict her as a young woman, in her wedding gown, and in costume. Also found are photographs of the Brinleys with, mostly unidentified, family and friends. Additional photographs are of Brinley in the military in Europe, and relatives of the Brinleys, including Daniel Putnam Brinley's mother and father, and Kathrine's brother Will Sanger and sister Emma Sanger. There is one photograph album of travels in California in 1902. Additional travel photographs are of trips to Canada, Bermuda, and Italy. Some photographs of Bermuda were taken in 1971 by Brinley's niece, Elizabeth Loder. Also found are photographs of the Brinley home, Datchet House, in New Canaan, Connecticut, their home in New York City, and an exterior photograph of John Erskine's studio. This series also includes a collection of reference photographs of artwork, murals, and frescoes from Churches in Italy, and a small number of photographs of artwork.
  This series has been partially scanned. Items not scanned include reference photographs, photographs of artwork, and negatives.
  - Photograph Portraits of Daniel Putnam Brinley, 1881-circa 1910, circa 1940s (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Daniel Putnam Brinley painting Murals, circa 1920s, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Photograph Portraits of Kathrine Sanger Brinley, 1897-circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Daniel Putnam Brinley & Kathrine Sanger Brinley with Family & Friends, 1890-circa 1940s (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Photographs of Daniel Putnam Brinley & Kathrine Sanger Brinley, circa 1905-1915, (Copyprints of Nitrate Negatives) (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Photographs of Daniel Putnam Brinley during Military Service, circa 1918, (Copyprints of Nitrate Negatives) (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Brinley & Sanger Families, circa 1890-1907 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Photograph Portraits of Others, 1893-circa 1921 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Photograph Album, "Pictures From California", 1902 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Photographs of Travels in Canada, 1937, (3 folders) (Box 13, Folder 27-29)
  - Photographs of Datchet House, circa early-1900s (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - Photographs of Home at 865 First Ave., 1932 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of John Erskine's Studio, 1926 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Photographs of Bermuda, 1921, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - Photographs of Italy, circa 1904-1908 (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Personal Photographs, 1895-1927 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Reference Photographs, (Not scanned) (Box 13)
    - Arezzo (Box 13, Folder 36)
    - Assisi (Box 13, Folder 37)
    - Atrani (Box 13, Folder 38)
    - Carcassone (Box 13, Folder 39)
    - Firenze (Florence) (Box 13, Folder 40)
    - Monreale (Box 13, Folder 41)
    - Montefalco (Box 13, Folder 42)
    - Montone (Box 13, Folder 43)
    - Padova (Box 13, Folder 44)
    - Palermo (Box 13, Folder 45)
    - Perugia (Box 13, Folder 46)
    - Pisa (Box 13, Folder 47)
    - Ravello (Box 13, Folder 48)
    - Ravenna (Box 13, Folder 49)
    - Roma (Box 13, Folder 50)
    - Siena (Box 13, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 52)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930s-1950s, (See also OV 22; not scanned) (Box 13, Folder 53)
  - Color Transparencies of Stained Glass Window, circa early-1900s, (Not scanned) (Box 13, Folder 54)
  - Photograph Negatives of Artwork, circa 1950s, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 14 (hol), Folder 1-2)
  - Photograph Negatives, Unidentified, circa 1970s, (Not scanned) (Box 14 (hol), Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930s-1950s, (See also Box 13, F53; not scanned) (Box OV 22)
- Artwork, 1891-1950s, Series 9:; (Box 14-15, OVs 18-21; 0.9 linear feet)
  This series contains artwork by Daniel Putnam Brinley and others, including six sketchbooks by Brinley. Three of the sketchbooks were used by Brinley while living in Paris and include ink and pencil drawings of landscapes, streetscapes, people, and animals. Sketchbook 4 was completed while he was working on Les Foyers Du Soldat in France and includes ink and pencil landscapes. Two additional sketchbooks, one which he titled "Away to Quebec," contain landscape sketches from his trips to Canada, including some watercolors. Additional loose drawings by Daniel Putnam Brinley include drawings for mural projects, landscapes, a drawing of a nude man, and sketches of "Willie's Operation." Also found in this series are several detailed mural studies for the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company building in New York City. Artwork by others include a drawing of Brinley by Albert Sterner, a drawing by Reinhold Palenske, and a lithograph by John Steuart Curry.
  - Sketchbook 1, circa 1905-1908 (Box 14 (hol), Folder 4)
  - Loose items from Sketchbook 1, circa 1905-1908 (Box 14 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook 2, circa 1905-1908 (Box 14 (hol), Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook 3, circa 1907 (Box 14 (hol), Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook 4, circa 1918 (Box 14 (hol), Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook 5, circa 1930s (Box 14 (hol), Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook, "Away to Quebec", 1935 (Box 14 (hol), Folder 10)
  - Mural Studies for Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, 1941, (See OV 19-21) (Box 14 (hol), Folder 11)
  - "Miniature Landscapes by Daniel Putnam Brinley", circa late-1950s (Box 14 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Artwork by Daniel Putnam Brinley, 1904-1941, (See also OV 18) (Box 15 (pam), Folder 1)
  - Artwork by Daniel Putnam Brinley, Undated, circa 1904-1941, (2 folders) (Box 15 (pam), Folder 2-3)
  - "Symbols and Emblems", circa 1940s (Box 15 (pam), Folder 4)
  - Artwork by Others, 1891-1937 (Box 15 (pam), Folder 5)
  - Hand-drawn Maps, 1907, early-1900s (Box 15 (pam), Folder 6)
  - Valentines, 1950, circa 1950s (Box 15 (pam), Folder 7)
  - Sketches by Kathrine Sanger Brinley, circa 1896-1898 (Box 15 (pam), Folder 8)
  - Artwork by Daniel Putnam Brinley, 1904-1941, (See also Box 15, F1) (Box OV 18)
  - Mural Studies for Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, 1941, (See also Box 14, F11) (Box OV 19-21)